

# **Curriculum Vitae for Robert Hagala**

#### Personal information

Address: Hagelundveien 5 E-mail: rh@xal.no

0963 Oslo Phone: +47 992 46 527

Born: 12 June 1991 Nationality: Norwegian

# **Summary**

I hold a PhD in astrophysics from the University of Oslo, where my field of research was large scale numerical N-body simulations. Through my research I have developed expertise in numerical modeling, statistical and visual analysis of big data sets, signal processing, pattern recognition, high- and low-level programming, and code optimization. I have learned many complex concepts in science and technology, and demonstrated my ability to understand and combine many areas of knowledge. I consider myself an analytical, adaptive, and open-minded person with the ability to work highly individually and quickly adapt to unforseen circumstances. I am experienced with having a holistic overview of a project, and at the same time being able to focus on details.

### **Technical skills**

Frameworks Numpy, Scipy, Flask, Matplotlib, MPI/OpenMP Languages Python, FORTRAN, C/C++, Java, PHP, R, Clojure

Tools Git, Unix, Windows, Jupyter Notebook, OpenOffice, LATEX, MSSQL,

Azure, CI/CD pipelines, Google

### **Education**

2015 - 2019	'Ph.D. in astrophysics (cosmology) at the University of Oslo, thesis tit-
	led "Astrophysical Simulations for Uncovering Signatures of Gravity".
	Supervisor: David F. Mota'
2013 - 2015	'M.Sc. in Astronomy at the University of Oslo, thesis titled "Cosmo-
	logical Simulations with Disformally Coupled Symmetron Fields".'
2010 - 2013	'B.Sc. in Physics, Astronomy and Meteorology" at the University of
	Oslo. Several extra courses in informatics.'

# **Professional experience**

2015 - 2019PhD student, University of Oslo. Developed and extended several pieces of high-performance parallel software for studying alternative theories of gravity. Collaborated in a highly international research field. 25% teaching duty in bachelor level astronomy course, including development of software for the students. 2012 - 2015Four semesters as group teacher (Teaching Assistant) in different courses at UiO and HiO (now OsloMet). Subjects include mathematics, physics and informatics. I answered questions about programming and science concepts, as well as graded exams. 2013 - 201427 % position as mathematics teacher with responsibility for a class of VG1 mathematics students. Blackboard and powerpoint lectures, and helping students with exercises. Designing and grading tests. Final grading of students. 2019 -Consultant, Expert Analytics

### Languages

**English** Fluent French Basic Native Norwegian Polish Intermediate

### Personal skills

Analytical and Good ability to understand and break down a new problem in a logical creative way, and to provide creative solutions when needed. Many years of experience in teaching science and programming. Good Communication and teaching ability to understand and explain difficult concepts. Intuitive and Not afraid to explore unknown problems and technology. Ability to get curious an overview and learn necessary material quickly. Modeling and Able to implement a physical model into computer code in an efficient data analysis way, while avoiding numerical problems. Developing custom tools to analyse the output and compare it with measurements.

#### Some interests and hobbies

Digital music editing, as well as several analog instruments including: drums, guitar, sitar, piano and gong

Personal development, learning and experiencing new things, traveling,

puzzles, cooking

Sports and Weightlifting, yoga, hiking, skiing, golf

nature

Music

Personal

### **Extended descriptions of selected projects**

Activity Automation of physical systems based on weather forecast

Period 2019 - 2020 Role Lead developer Staffing Team of 4

Description A cloud based application for modelling and optimising an automated

industrial control system. The application can be accessed from a compatible system through a RESTful API; the cloud application performs a calculation based on online weather data and physical models, and returns the calculated optimal parameters for the automated system. I developed most of the physical model, and implemented the cloud based application from scratch. I was also responsible for assessing and minimising security risks, developing a complete testing pipeline,

as well as writing user documentation.

Tools Python, Azure Web App, Azure SQL, physical modelling (meteorology,

thermodynamics)

Activity Cosmological simulations with scalar fields

Period 2013 - 2019 Role Researcher Staffing Team of 3

Description Together with my supervisors (David Mota and Claudio Llinares), I

extended the freely available cosmological N-body code RAMSES to simulate an additional disformal scalar degree of freedom. This introduces a highly non-linear hyperbolic differential equation for the scalar field, as well as complex equations for the extra forces on the N-body particles. RAMSES is written in FORTRAN, and is designed to run in parallel on supercomputing clusters. Hence, I paid special attention to memory usage, efficient MPI parallelism, and low level code optimization. The output data ranged from gigabytes to terabytes, and statistical analysis of the output was necessary to draw scientific conclusions. I wrote several auxillary tools for data and image analysis, as well as a 1-dimensional hyperbolic solver in spherical symmetry for more detailed study of the non-linear equation of motion of the scalar

field.

Tools Physical modeling, statistical data analysis, image analysis, scientific

writing, FORTRAN, Python

Activity Development and use of student software: AST2000 Mission Control

Period 2015 - 2017

Role Developer and tester

Staffing Team of 8

Description

As part of my work as a group teacher in AST1100/AST2000, I had a leading role as developer of the Python backend that the students used for visualisation. The code procedurally generates a virtual solar system for each student, and during the course the student interacts with this code to launch a satellite from one planet, achieve orbit around another planet and land a landing module safely. After finishing development and writing the exercises and user manual, I had the main responsibility for updating the codebase when students reported bugs and inconsistencies.

Tools

Analytical modeling, procedural generation, user interfacing, pedagogical writing, Python, LaTeX